United States Department of Agriculture / WSU Palouse Conservation Field Station and Agricultural Research Service Records 1931-1977
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
United States Department of Agriculture / WSU Palouse Conservation Field Station and Agricultural Research Service Records
1931-1977
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Archives 258
2 linear feet 2 containers
Collection includes Annual Research Reports for the Palouse Conservation Field Station from 1931 to 1971..
History:
The Palouse Conservation Field Station began as a joint project between the United States Department of Agriculture and the State College of Washington in 1931. At that time it was called the Pacific Northwest Soil Erosion and Moisture Conservation Experiment Station. In 1935, the name was shortened to the Soil Conservation Experiment Station. In the following decades, the name shifted back and forth several times to also include the Soil and Water Conservation Research Station and many derivations thereof. In 1961, the name was switched to the Palouse Conservation Field Station. During their tenure, the Palouse Conservation Field Station conducted experiments to produce better farming techniques that would produce less runoff and erosion, and wou ld make more efficient use of water for farming purposes. The Agricultural Experiment Station at the University of Idaho also worked with the U.S.D.A. to conduct experiments in a similar vein.
Records of the Palouse Conservation Field Station consist of annual and other reports, along with compilations of data.
Annual Research Reports for the Palouse Conservation Field Station are filed in chronological order from 1931-1971. Subsequent data reports relating to PCFS, are filed corresponding to their first year of reporting. Reports for the Agricultural Experi ment Station follow this, as do reports of a joint project between WSU and the Agricultural Research Service.
The Collection is open for research use.
Records of the Palouse Conservation Field Station and the Agricultural Research Service were transferred to the University Libraries in 2000 as Accession UA2000-20.
Washington State University --Palouse Conservation Field Station--Records and correspondence.
Soil conservation -- Northwest, Pacific.
Washington (State); Colleges and Universities; Environmental Conditions
- Annual Research Reports, variously titled
  - Progress Report, Pacific Northwest Soil Erosion and Moisture Conservation Experiment Station (W.A. Rockie), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Engineering Experiments (P.C. McGrew), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - (Rockie, McGrew), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Engineering Experiments, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - (C.E. Deardorff), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Engineering Experiments, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - (Deardorff, McGrew), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Soil Conservation Experiment Station (Glenn Horner, P.C. McGrew), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Soil and Water Conservation Experiment Station (Horner), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Soil Conservation Experiment Station, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Soil and Water Conservation Research Station (Glenn M. Horner, Loy M. Naffziger), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Summary of Results, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - (Glenn M. Horner, Lloyd M. Cox, Earle E. Cary), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Palouse Conservation Field Station, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - (Stephen J. Mech, et al.), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Program Management Report included, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Other Reports
  - Memos and Notes on Soil Sampling, 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Map of Pacific Northwest Soil Erosion Experiment Station, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Progress Report 1931-1935, Pacific Northwest Soil Conservation Experiment Station (McGrew, Horner) (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Results of Soil and Water Conservation Studies in the Northwest 1931-1935 (McGrew, Horner) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Progress Report 1931-1942, Soil and Water Conservation Experiment Station (Horner) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Watershed and Surface Runoff Data, 1931-1947 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Annual Report, Pacific Northwest Erosion Control Projects, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Tables, Annual History of Experimental Area, Palouse Soil and Water Conservation Farm
    - 1936 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - 1937 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Program Management Report, Palouse Conservation Field Station
    - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - 1965 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Annual Report, Agricultural Experiment Station
    - (J. Marvin Rosa), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - (Rosa, V.O. Thompson), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - 1965 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Annual Progress Reports, Agricultural Research Service and Washington State University Joint Projects, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Work Reporting Unit Annual Report and Plan, Agricultural Research Service-Western Region
    - FY 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - FY 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - FY 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - FY 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Oversize
  - Tables, Rainfall levels in Pullman, WA, 1932-1954 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Tables, Annual History of Experimental Area, Palouse Soil and Water Conservation Farm
    - 1936 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - 1937 (Box 2, Folder 65)